Hello. I'm your host David Barnard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in
RevenueCat's state of subscription apps
report. Each episode in this series will
explore one crucial metric and share
actionable insights from top
subscription app operators. With me
today, Tammy Toh, product and business
growth consultant on the Google Play
team. On the podcast, I talked with
Tammy about diversifying revenue beyond
subscriptions. What Google Play's data
reveals about buyer behavior and why
lower price points can actually increase
total revenue. Hey Tammy, thanks so much
for joining me today. Thank you for
having me, David. This is my first
podcast, so I'm excited to be here. I
want to kick off talking about the Play
Store very specifically. And I think
it's really cool how much the Google
Play team, and I know there's like
multiple teams across Google doing this,
but have been sharing more and more
resources and insights and statistics
over the last few years. And so, that's
what I want to kick it off with is to to
kind of get the insiders take having
worked with so many developers and
looking at the data internally. From
your perspective, what's the best way
for app developers to succeed on the
Play Store? I find that being an Android
user, admittedly I also have an iOS
device. And so, you could see some of
the differences in terms of just the not
just the app, but how users use the
phone. There's not one solution for
every type of user and an easier way to
parse that is by platform. And so, if
you can look at metrics and KPIs and
your performance across these two
separate platforms or other platforms
you might have, you'll notice that the
behavior is very different. No one
solution fits all users. So, you do need
revenue diversification strategies. So,
before you do that, I do think it's
important to optimize your subscription
business. So, and that's because a lot
of app developers are only offering
subscriptions. But what we're starting
to notice in Eastern markets, Asia,
Africa, the Middle East, that the buyer
types look different. Not all users are
buying subscriptions and instead they're
buying consumable IAPs. And so, the next
step after optimizing subscription, once
you know you've kind of saturated that,
most of your users are not willing to
buy month-to-month or reoccurring price
points, maybe they have an appetite for
these one-time only purchases. And so,
what we're starting to see in the data
in these markets is that almost half of
users are buying consumable IAPs versus
subscriptions. And that they're not just
buying these consumable IAPs
one time, they're buying it over and
over again. What does that look like
across different categories? Do you see
certain categories have higher
propensity to spend in those ways? So,
right now, at least in the data, comics,
dating, social, and tooling apps are
ones that have more consumable features.
So, for example, in social, you can gift
and tip the creators. In dating, like
you can get boosted or you can send
flowers to someone that you think is
special and you want their attention.
And so, those apps also are the ones
that have adopted this model pretty
early on. And so, that's probably why
we're seeing a lot of the success there.
But I like to argue that in other
categories, you can also mimic this
business model. It's just that you have
to think through on what makes sense and
what will work. So, I think, for
example, like health and fitness, in the
real world, in person, you can buy class
that will go away. So, you're starting
to see this with other types of
applications as well. It's a really good
example of like a a health and fitness
app selling a package of six classes
instead of a subscription. And then, you
know, I've actually been seeing that and
maybe this hasn't, you know, quite shown
up in the data yet, where if it's
something that's really computationally
expensive for the developer to provide,
you know, photo creation apps, they're
selling a pack of 25 creations and those
are consumable and they go away. And so,
for certain business cases, especially
those like really high resource
intensive things like AI, these kind of
models work really well and align with
the benefits.
To your point, resource-based or um
quantifiable. So, AI is a great example
of that in terms of like the number of
messaging or inquiries a user inputs, so
that takes computational resource. I
think you can even think about it in the
sense of the streaming apps that offer
different quality videos for a different
price point. So, for for example, like
you don't get as good as quality as 4K
unless you pay maybe $10 more. And I
think there's a good amount of media and
entertainment apps that do that even on
the in the audio space as well. For
developers considering switching to a
hybrid model, there's probably a lot of
trepidation and, you know, what are some
of the things you've seen as far as
tradeoffs, but then also like we've kind
of already been talking about like where
you've seen it be more successful. But
what are the tradeoffs and maybe gotchas
to be watching out for if a developer
wants to experiment with a more hybrid
monetization model? Yeah, I think the
key is you have to go in with the
mindset of experimenting and to evaluate
where your risks are. And so, what we
have seen or what developers have
expressed to us as concern is the
cannibalization of the subscription
business, which is a valid concern, but
you don't want to take away from people
who are willing to pay a month-to-month
fee or a reoccurring fee to the smaller
bite-size type transaction. I like to
argue that there's a different types of
users. Everyone has a different wallet
size. And once you get you've kind of
saturated or exhausted all the users who
are willing to pay in a reoccurring
basis, then there's opportunity to grab
more users that just don't have the
means to pay for something in a
reoccurring basis. So, I like to think
that we can optimize the area under the
demand curve with different price points
that fits users' needs. So, thinking
through, you know, these buyer cohorts
will help with some of those concerns
about cannibalizing. I also think, you
know, you've got to really think through
what you're offering to that user. I
think repeat purchase mechanics are
great for that consumable transaction
that you want users to do. So, it is a
little harder when you're trying to
offer like, here's this paintbrush for a
lifetime, then you don't have much left
to offer. And so, you're kind of
limiting the use there. What are the
holistic features of your app that can
be bite-size that users still find value
that will mitigate some of the risks of,
you know, getting users to not buy the
subscription. I think that's something
where, you know, dating apps were kind
of early to this with Tinder being the
most famous example that we've already
talked about that super boosts and
things like that were were really
innovative at that time of like layering
on that additional monetization. And
then, kind of as you said, kind of a
double-edged sword where, yes, you may
cannibalize some subscriptions, but then
you also open up the opportunity to way
better monetize those people who are
willing to pay more. And the the tricky
thing about a subscription, too, is is
that people get differing amounts of
value from your product. So, if you're a
a note-taking app like Notion, it's like
somebody who's using it to power their
entire business gets way more valuable,
way more value out of it than somebody
who's like using it as a diary. And for
certain products, there's not always a
great way to distinguish between those
use cases, but when you can and figure
out tiering structures and the
consumables or one-time purchases and
other stuff, you're better aligning the
monetization with the people who get the
most value. So, even if some people pay
less, you create the opportunity for
other people to pay even more. Is that
what you've seen in the data as well?
Exactly. And the users who are already
buying the subscription and then they
top it off or complement it with
features like a booster or whatnot, we
call those hybrid buyers. And what we've
seen is that, yes, they make up a small
percentage of total buyers. The
exception is with dating, but it's a
little different use case. But they like
annually make up three times more than a
what a subscriber would pay because your
cap with a subscription model, those
users can't buy anymore. So, they can't
spend anymore even if they wanted to and
saw value, too. And so, they typically
users who buy both typically spend three
times more than a subscriber and three
times more than users who just buy IAPs.
And so, I understand that the other
concern is that you'll lower your
average revenue per paying user by
introducing more models, but the upside
is in the tradeoff I think it's
important to evaluate is that you will
increase your buyer percentage. And so,
you have to kind of understand where you
are in that maturity state of your
business and what tradeoffs are you
willing to make. So, we've been talking
at kind of a higher level of
monetization and strategy and things
like that, but getting into tactics,
between your team and I know you you
work with a lot of other teams inside
Google Play, what are the specific
tactics or what's the advice you give or
you've heard colleagues talk about when
folks are looking to improve their
monetization on Play? I have to have
like a three-pronged approach and we
talked about this at our developer
conference called Playtime. Um that's
usually held at the end of the year.
When we advise developers to provide
them like benchmarking on how they're
performing against their peers at there
we see underperformance and then we see
room for growth, but we advise is like
first and foremost, obviously, optimize
your existing business, right? So, how
can you optimize subscription beyond
what you're already offering? So, we
think about it in several ways, whether
that's a payment like adding more
payment methods beyond just the credit
card. At Play, we're starting to offer
other ways that users can buy. For
example, like installments. Users can
buy a whole year, but then they still
pay for a monthly they still pay on a
monthly basis. So, that gives them the
benefit of paying the yearly price,
which is much cheaper than the monthly
price and they're committed to just
paying on a monthly basis. And then, the
others are, you know, the type of intro
offer that you're offering your users.
Is it a trial? Is it a discount? How
much is the discount? How long is the
trial? Those are things that you can
test. And the other thing that we see
more often is like localizing the prices
in those top markets. So, emerging
market prices are about 40% lower than
developed markets. And so, be very
cognizant, especially in markets that
you see rapid new user growth, that you
are fitting your prices to that market.
So, whether it's willingness to pay,
cultural differences, and/or the price
of alternatives and substitutes in those
markets. And then, once you've optimized
on that subscription business, then you
can start thinking about where does it
make sense to introduce in-app purchases
or consumable transactions? What
trade-off am I willing to take? If I
increase my buyer percentage, is it okay
if my average revenue per paying user
goes down? And so, you need to calculate
some of those LTVs and see what you're
willing to trade off for that benefit.
And obviously, think about your cost of
acquiring the users, the cost of
operating, and things like that to see
where you can take that risk. What we've
been seeing is that hybrid buyers do
There is users who are interested in
paying more if they especially see value
in your app. And so, sometimes it a
small percentage of buyers, the
average stat that we see is they they
make up about 7% of total buyers, but
they can bring in a quarter of the
revenue, um which is pretty impressive.
In kicking off these kind of experiments
and thinking about broadening the
monetization model and and experimenting
with different offers and things like
that that you were just talking about,
what are the things to watch out for?
The biggest one, you give your users so
many options or choices on ways to
convert, they probably will have some
decision paralysis, and they will
probably take a whole year to decide
what they need. And so, obviously, in
terms of price discrimination laws, you
need to present the same prices and same
offers to everyone. However, I think
what you can be strategic about is how
you offer it during their user journey,
right? Are there any signals that you
can say, okay, this user most likely
will take a monthly SKU, or this user
might not be so comfortable with the
monthly SKU. Can I
prioritize the weekly SKU for them?
Obviously, you won't know those signals
right at the first hour of that user
experience, but maybe you can gauge it
over there, especially if you're a
freemium app, you can gauge it over some
time based on how they're using the app.
You can have some kind of decision tree
as those users are going through that
first-time user experience, when you
offer that type of offer that you think
they'll most likely convert on. Once you
finally get a user to transact, that
you're done with that user, definitely
continue to optimize that buyer's
experience, cuz
whether it's a reoccurring SKU or
one-time transaction, you want them to
continue to pay. To get that loyalty,
you need to show that loyalty back to
the customer. Yeah, that's fantastic
advice. And I think as the industry
matures and just as time passes, this is
going to be more and more of a thing. If
for the apps that truly generate value
in people's lives and that kind of leave
a good impression on the user, like as
you're thinking about long-term strategy
and kind of leaving users with a good
taste in their mouth, that in the long
arc, a lot of people are going to start
coming back to some of these apps that
they've abandoned. And so, even
longer-term win-backs will be more and
more of a thing as the subscription app
industry matures over time. Awesome.
Well, is there anything else you want to
share as we wrap up? I know I threw a
lot of stats out for developers that do
have that support Android. One, thank
you. And two is there's a lot of
information in the Play Console. I think
people forget what you can find there.
We actually have a lot of benchmarking
data in there. So, if you want to see
how you are performing against a peer
set or a different category outside
yours, you can look at some of your
KPIs, especially around Play Store
conversion rates, and you can see how
you're performing against your peers.
The few other ones that we have is the
Play Academy, where if you are a small
developer trying to get started, and
even if you're a larger one, there are a
lot of courses in Play Academy that you
can learn about how to acquire users,
how to monetize, different monetization
tactics that we talked about earlier.
And then, at the end of the year, the
Play team hosts a conference that we
call Playtime in different regions
around the world. And so, we share a lot
of the insights that you heard today at
those conferences, as well. Awesome. So,
we'll include links to all of that in
the show notes for people to be able
just click into. And yeah, it's been
really cool to see how much Google Play
teams are sharing. And I got to go to
Google I/O for the first time this year,
which was an incredible conference. So,
don't sleep on all the resources Google
is putting out. You know, it seems like
incentives are aligned, you know? It's
great for Google Play to have good apps
that are monetizing well, and it's cool
to see Google really leaning into that
and kind of helping developers more and
more with all of these resources. Yeah,
definitely. I'm excited that you get to
come to I/O. If it's similar to last
year, hopefully get to present the same
content that we presented at the end of
this past year, which is around
resubscriber trends, and that there
isn't quite the subscriber fatigue that
all the headlines are saying. All right,
thanks so much for joining me, Tammy.
This was super insightful, and I think,
you know, folks who do have apps on the
Play Store are going to get a lot out of
this. And hopefully, you know, increase
monetization in 2025. So, thanks for
sharing all these insights. Thank you.